<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Wishes Ultd. - musings</title>
    <subtitle>Indie games by Greg Lobanov &amp; friends</subtitle>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://gl326.github.io/web/tags/musings/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://gl326.github.io/web/"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2023-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://gl326.github.io/web/tags/musings/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Greg&#x27;s Cool Games from 2023 </title>
        <published>2023-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-12-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/gregs-cool-games-from-2023/"/>
        <id>https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/gregs-cool-games-from-2023/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/gregs-cool-games-from-2023/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(This is part of my “Game Musings” newsletter where I write thoughts about game design and development. If you just want news and updates on my projects, you can &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;greglobanov.substack.com&#x2F;account&quot;&gt;edit your subscription here.&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With 2023 coming to a close, I wanted to take a moment to shout out some exciting games that came out this year! I do try to take the time to play lots of games, as it helps fuel my work with diverse ideas… this year I also helped out jurying the Independent Games Festival (IGF) which exposed me to a TON of cool games I would have otherwise missed. This is not an exhaustive list of every game I liked, or even a proper ranked list or anything… this list also excludes games made by any friends of mine. These are just some really cool games I recommend in no particular order! OK??? OK!!!! &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Also note that all(?) of these games are on sale…. right now!!!)&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;store.steampowered.com&#x2F;app&#x2F;1617220&#x2F;Thirsty_Suitors&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Thirsty Suitors&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Available on Steam, Switch, Xbox, Playstation… and also on GamePass (I think)!! I played on Switch.&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Thirsty Suitors, you play as kind of a garbage-fire college-age skateboard punk with a rocky relationship history who abruptly comes back home after several years and has to deal with the fallout of all her past mistakes. You’ll be skating around town to visit friends, cooking dishes to impress your parents, and hashing out your emotional baggage in turn-based RPG battles. The writing is some of my favorite I’ve seen in a game in a long time, and the animation is also outstanding. It’s outrageously funny and gets really personal as well.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;store.steampowered.com&#x2F;app&#x2F;1931770&#x2F;Chants_of_Sennaar&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Chants of Sennaar&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Available on Steam, Switch, PS4, Xbox&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;A game about deciphering language! As you explore and climb a Tower of Babel, you’ll be exposed to different symbols and it’s up to you to use context to slowly piece together what they each mean so you can navigate a foreign world. What’s most remarkable to me is how &lt;em&gt;NOT&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; daunting this game is - it’s very precisely crafted and paced so that every step from bottom to top was a satisfying little puzzle. (That must have been &lt;em&gt;VERY&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; hard to do!!! Games like this are usually very obtuse!!). It also introduces a number of different languages which each express subtle and interesting details about the cultures they represent, from the way the symbols are shaped to the grammar of their sentences. It’s very well thought out and very engrossing to play… I could NOT put it down and wound up 100%ing it in one long session. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;store.steampowered.com&#x2F;app&#x2F;1705140&#x2F;Final_Profit_A_Shop_RPG&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Final Profit: A Shop RPG&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;3.png&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Available on Steam and itch.io&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;You’re Queen of the elves, except the elvish kingdom is languishing under the boot of the Bureau of Business, a powerful and shadowy organization of businessmen who control seemingly everything. So you hatch a plan to destroy them by becoming the BEST at business. Hilarity ensues as you fall deeper and deeper into the rabbit-hole of economics, finding new and exciting ways to exploit people and optimize your finances. It’s an ugly-aesthetic RPGMaker game but I’d argue that its cheap veneer only adds to this game’s sublime charm. If you like managing inventories, collecting resources and numbers going up then you will get a LOT out of this game, and a lot of good laughs along with it. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;store.steampowered.com&#x2F;app&#x2F;1240060&#x2F;A_Highland_Song&#x2F;&quot;&gt;A Highland Song&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;4.png&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Available on Steam and Switch!&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;A story-rich side-scrolling adventure where you play as Moira, a runaway girl on a journey to find her uncle in a distant lighthouse in the Scottlish highlands. Along the way you’ll come across abandoned towns, dim caverns, strange people, ghosts, folklore and most importantly, MAPS! This game is all about getting lost and finding your way through ambiguous directions and sketchy maps that can point out hidden shortcuts or send you even further off the trail. It’s hard to capture what’s really special about this game because it’s succeeding in a way I have a hard time comparing to anything else. For a side-scrolling game it does an exceptional job of capturing the vast feeling of a 3D open-world game, but rich with little stories and discoveries that make every moment a delight. There’s also inexplicably great musical game elements while you sprint through the fields as fauna run alongside you. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;store.steampowered.com&#x2F;app&#x2F;1321440&#x2F;Cassette_Beasts&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Cassette Beasts&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;5.png&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Steam, Switch and Xbox&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;A monster-taming open-world turn-based RPG! You find yourself thrown into a strange world under threat by giant glitchy hellbeasts where people can “record” monsters and transform into them! The game has a couple standout features, namely: when your meter’s full, you can fuse any two beasts to create a temporary new super-beast! And, every beast has its own type(s) which have advantages and disadvantages against other type(s), but the way every type interacts is unique and creative - for example, a fire move can melt a plastic-type beast and lower their offense. This game offers satisfying open-ended exploration and cool strategic battles as well. I had my gripes with it, but as someone who has been looking into many different games of this format, this one stands out quite a bit. And for anyone following the development of &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;store.steampowered.com&#x2F;app&#x2F;1864950&#x2F;Beastieball&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Beastieball&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, I strongly recommend this game to enjoy in the meantime!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Games to watch for next year….&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve also had the opportunity to see a lot of games that aren’t quite done yet! I recommend you keep an eye on these next year.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;6.png&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;thecatamites.itch.io&#x2F;anthology-of-the-killer&quot;&gt;Anthology of the Killer&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; - A collection of short story games about a zine artist in a surreal murder-friendly world. They’re weird, witty, incredibly funny, and incredibly well-paced too. There’s a potent creative energy here that harkens to zine culture or, at least to me, the wild world webcomics. 8 out of 9 episodes are actually already available! But with the release of the final episode it will be collected into a single handy anthology experience which might be worth waiting for. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;store.steampowered.com&#x2F;app&#x2F;1206070&#x2F;Phonopolis&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Phonopolis&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; - This is a game by a new team under the umbrella of Amanaita Design, known for titles like Samorost and Machinarium. Phonopolis is an incredibly exciting project full of playful interactive dioramas and character animation. The art direction is just divine.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;store.steampowered.com&#x2F;app&#x2F;1675830&#x2F;1000xRESIST&#x2F;&quot;&gt;1000xRESIST&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;- An intense and high-concept walk-and-talk game about a cult of clones in a post-apocalypse underground bunker. A lot of the game revolves around exploring memories and piecing together the history of your cult and the apocalypse that birthed it, and it quickly gets into some heavy and confronting things. It’s as resonant and compelling as some of the best Prestige TV I’ve seen but constructed out of many creative interactive setpieces. The dev team comes from a background in stage performance and that skillset comes through really clearly here.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;See ya next year!&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have so many other articles and things I wanted to write up this year that I just couldn’t make the time for. But, I want to thank everyone following my newsletters and everyone who’s sent in a nice comment or reply too. It’s been really fun for me to have a space like this to collect my thoughts and talk more about what’s exciting to me in games lately. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;More to come soon! :) Happy new year~&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>10 years of Roguelike Deckbuilders</title>
        <published>2023-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/10-years-of-roguelike-deckbuilders/"/>
        <id>https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/10-years-of-roguelike-deckbuilders/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/10-years-of-roguelike-deckbuilders/">&lt;p&gt;Coin Crypt, the world’s first roguelike deckbuilder, is 10 years old today!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I was making it at the time, it seemed a totally off-the-wall combination of ideas and genres, but one I was fascinated by and kept falling deeper and deeper into. A seemingly endless design space where every idea would beget even more ideas. I put everything I could into it, thinking it was up to me to explore the space I’d found. I had no idea that later it would become its own genre, let alone one that nowadays gets labelled as crowded and competitive.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Coin Crypt has always been a lesser-known title and in the grand scheme I really can’t take credit for inspiring anything that came after because I’m pretty sure none of those later works were aware of it, LOL. But I always have been proud of it and I think it is a pretty dang cool game. Of all my works it’s still the one I would most readily want to boot up and play again, 10 years later. It’s definitely needlessly opaque, but it’s also full of fun ideas that still stand apart from genre contemporaries.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To commemorate the anniversary, I was interviewed by a blog called Sunken Shrine, which has been exploring the history of the genre and identified Coin Crypt as the earliest entry. Check it out here! &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;div id=&quot;youtube2-UJeSczCQ1HE&quot; class=&quot;youtube-wrap&quot; data-attrs=&quot;{&amp;quot;videoId&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;UJeSczCQ1HE&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;startTime&amp;quot;:null,&amp;quot;endTime&amp;quot;:null}&quot; data-component-name=&quot;Youtube2ToDOM&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;youtube-inner&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube-nocookie.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;UJeSczCQ1HE?rel=0&amp;amp;autoplay=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&amp;amp;enablejsapi=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; gesture=&quot;media&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; fullscreen&quot; allowautoplay=&quot;true&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; width=&quot;728&quot; height=&quot;409&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re curious to check the game out, it’s &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;store.steampowered.com&#x2F;app&#x2F;264690&#x2F;Coin_Crypt&#x2F;&quot;&gt;available on Steam! &lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But in the spirit of recommending roguelike deckbuilders, I’d really like to shout out more recent exceptional games that have both tightened the design and introduced more storytelling into the mix:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;store.steampowered.com&#x2F;app&#x2F;2179850&#x2F;Cobalt_Core&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Cobalt Core&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which features spaceships on a small tactics grid, just came out this month.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;store.steampowered.com&#x2F;app&#x2F;1092790&#x2F;Inscryption&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Inscryption&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is a thrilling and gorgeous adventure with many twists and turns.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although not a &lt;em&gt;roguelike&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;store.steampowered.com&#x2F;app&#x2F;1058690&#x2F;Signs_of_the_Sojourner&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Signs of the Sojourner&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is a brilliant take on deckbuilding &amp;amp; card games with emotionally resonant storytelling.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Happy carding!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Open-World Storytelling (Struggles)</title>
        <published>2023-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/open-world-storytelling-struggles/"/>
        <id>https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/open-world-storytelling-struggles/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/open-world-storytelling-struggles/">&lt;p&gt;This past month has been a big one for us &amp;amp; &lt;em&gt;Beastieball&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. I spent a fair amount of time designing, scripting and laying out the game’s ending sequences - and as a result of my labour &lt;em&gt;Beastieball&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; (finally) has an ending and is a beatable game from start to finish!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s a major milestone for sure, but there’s still a long road to having a finished video game. Especially because of the game’s open-ended nature, a lot of what we have feels more like an outline that still needs filling in. In particular, I’m most concerned with doing more work on the story and world-building over the course of the adventure. Typically in these newsletters I try to share what wisdom I’ve accrued from experience… but this time I’d like to be a little more candid and share aspects of this game that are still ongoing challenges for us.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The stories in my games are almost always the focus of the project and something we put a lot of care into. I’ve tackled a lot of different game genres and story presentations. Notably, the second half of &lt;em&gt;Chicory&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; presents several major story threads that can each be experienced in any order. After the success of that experiment, I felt more confident stepping into &lt;em&gt;Beastieball&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; with the plan to have almost all of the game’s events be unordered. I’ve never really loved the storytelling in the open-world games that I’ve played, but I was excited to take the narrative design experience I have and apply it to that problem to see what I could do. But I didn’t anticipate all the ways that I’d be challenged by the process along the way! &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;For starters - because any given event could be visited at any time, each event often has to be written with very little outside context. In my past games, I always had a clear picture of the journey over the course of the adventure; which parts are happy, which parts are sad, what the protagonist is feeling when they first reach a location and what happens to them there. &lt;em&gt;Wandersong&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Chicory&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Phantasmaburbia &lt;&#x2F;em&gt;all feature dramatic story reveals followed by sections that reckon with the fallout of those events - and that context shapes how small interactions with every NPC was written, the mood of the music in certain areas, etc. While there is an overarching plot which connects the smaller events of Beastieball, we don’t always know &lt;em&gt;where&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; each step of the story will happen for each player, so we don’t get to have that added direction for every area and character in the story.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The protagonist themself is fully customized and named by the player - and has no formal dialogue of their own, so that the player can project themselves into the story. We want players to express themselves through their Beastie recruit selections, their Beastieball strategies, and the ways that they explore - but what we lose is that there is no central protagonist whose shifting emotions and perspective can guide the story. Instead we put the focus on the characters you meet along the way. Ironically, even though this is by far the largest adventure I’ve worked on, it is necessarily constructed out of the smallest pieces of self-contained stories in different parts of the map.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;But the challenge that I least anticipated was how much the storytelling is beholden to the structure of the game itself. Because every piece of the story is small and self-contained in different areas, we have to devote an outsized portion of the wordcount just on instructing the player and pointing them in the right direction so that they know what to do next. I’ve hinted at this challenge in &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;greglobanov.substack.com&#x2F;p&#x2F;game-musings-quest-logs-pt-2&quot;&gt;previous newsletters&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, but it’s exacerbated by having so many small “quests” that don’t relate to each other. In larger linear games, players eventually fall into a pattern where they generally know the direction they’re going in, and the game can explain a little less and start to have more breathing room for flavor. That’s not quite the case in open-world games like &lt;em&gt;Beastieball&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, and at times as a writer it can be suffocating!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the bigger picture… The best stories are always built on surprises. If you already know what’s going to happen, there’s no suspense or excitement pulling you forward. But &lt;em&gt;games&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; are the opposite; if you don’t know where to go next or what to do, it quickly gets frustrating and boring as you go in circles without a clear purpose in mind. An open-world game where the player can do things in any order therefore needs to establish clear goals for the player in every direction, and at its heart needs to fall into some type of repetitive structure or pattern the player can learn to recognize, ie. “defeat the big boss in each area.” While there are many cool surprises in store in &lt;em&gt;Beastieball, &lt;&#x2F;em&gt;larger structural necessities like these are always exerting force against us.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;3.png&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Every story always comes with its own challenges, of course. And to some extent, it’s true that if the process for anything is easy, then you’re not really doing anything ambitious. But there are also a lot of hidden compromises that come with the decisions we made about this game early on, and we are at the point where we need to accept those compromises and move forward with the best version we can create. There are many amazing things about this game which will only be possible because of those compromises, too. Ultimately we have to find a path and plan that leverages the game’s potential strengths the most, rather than spotlighting its weaknesses. This project has done a lot to show me my limits as a creator, but I’m still loving the challenge and optimistic that at the end of our struggles we’ll produce something truly excellent.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wish us luck!!!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Designing Hidden Information</title>
        <published>2023-08-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-08-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/designing-hidden-information/"/>
        <id>https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/designing-hidden-information/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/designing-hidden-information/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hidden information&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; has got to be one of the coolest trenches to explore in the vast sea of game design study. Put simply, it’s the information you don’t know in a game. In many card games, every player knows what’s been played on the board, but won’t know what’s waiting in their opponent’s hands. Chess is famous as a game with “no” hidden information… although partly what’s made the game thrilling for thousands of years is the fact that you can never know what’s going on in your opponent’s head.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s also a design topic that’s often invisible to players, because when the game isn’t presenting info to you, you don’t know that you don’t know it. What information is and isn’t visible to a player fundamentally shapes their experience of that game… in a certain light, all game design comes down to this subject in some way or another.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I had to dig deep into this trench as part of the design process for &lt;em&gt;Beastieball!&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Screenshot: Pokemon Showdown, an online Pokemon battle simulator&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;Beastieball’s design lineage is mostly from JRPGs, like &lt;em&gt;Pokemon&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, which are generally very &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;greglobanov.substack.com&#x2F;p&#x2F;game-musings-squishy-and-crunchy&quot;&gt;“squishy,”&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; creating lots of space for minor statistical variations that make every player’s experience feel unique. One of the simple ways that surfaces is in &lt;strong&gt;damage calculation. &lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;In most RPGs, like &lt;em&gt;Final Fantasy, Pokemon, Chrono Trigger, Earthbound,&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; or heck, even &lt;em&gt;Dark Souls… &lt;&#x2F;em&gt;dealing damage can feel a bit like a slot machine, where the player inputs an attack, and then finds out how much damage their attack resulted in. Often there’s a bit of randomness added in, so that the same character hitting the same enemy over and over produces varying amounts of damage with each swing. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This way of revealing the damage dealt is another form of hidden information, and one which contributes to the fun of those games. In &lt;em&gt;Pokemon&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, for example, you’ll learn to intuit how much damage your attacks will do, being able to predict for example that your super-effective fire attack will probably take down the opposing grass-type in one hit. In high-skill &lt;em&gt;Pokemon&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; competitions, players compete with a vast amount of knowledge and intuition, being able to identify almost exactly how much damage any interaction between any two Pokemon will have - indeed, this ability to accurately foresee the outcome of any given attack is often what makes the difference between victory and defeat. Not to mention all the various “surprise” events that can occur which players also have to account for, like critical hits.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While understanding that this huge space of hidden information is part of what makes these games enjoyable, I really wanted to go in a different direction with &lt;em&gt;Beastieball. &lt;&#x2F;em&gt;Surprise is fun, but it’s also opaque; it’s frustrating when you lose to something you simply couldn’t see coming, like an unexpected critical hit, or a mysterious interaction with an enemy ability you haven’t seen before. More hidden information also means players spend more of their early experience with the game feeling lost and confused, not yet knowing how or why things are happening, and more than anything I wanted &lt;em&gt;Beastieball&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; to be accessible to new players.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Screenshot: &lt;em&gt;Into the Breach&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; by Subset Games&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This speaks to a trend I’ve observed with a lot of recent high-profile, designer-friendly games like &lt;em&gt;Slay the Spire&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Into the Breach. &lt;&#x2F;em&gt;In the above &lt;em&gt;Breach&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; screenshot, while the player is selecting their actions for their turn, they can already see red arrows indicating exactly what every enemy will do; the two bugs highlighted in red will attack a player unit, and two new enemies are about to come up from underground on the right side of the board. Players are allowed to strategize their actions however they want already knowing exactly what their opponent will do. It creates a satisfying, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;greglobanov.substack.com&#x2F;p&#x2F;game-musings-squishy-and-crunchy&quot;&gt;crunchy&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; space almost more akin to a puzzle game than a strategy game. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course, these games are brilliantly and carefully designed to exclude just the right amount of info, too; for example, you don’t know WHAT enemies are going to pop out of the ground, nor is it obvious that the opponent insect attacks will also light the forest under your feet on fire. Tell the player too much and the game feels disorienting with info, or perhaps hyper-linear, leaving no space for surprise, discovery or creativity.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unlike &lt;em&gt;Slay the Spire&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Into the Breach, Beastieball&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; needed to support player vs. player as well as single-player encounters (a totally separate rabbit hole for other articles…). This meant that we couldn’t outright tell the player what their opponent was going to do, because part of the fundamental design is that their opponent might be another player who is deciding their next action at the same time. But I did go out of my way to reveal as much as I could, down to revealing exactly how much damage any given attack will do before the player commits to it - and being able to see how much damage opponents can do to them, too.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;3.png&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Beastieball shows exactly how much damage your attack will do… to a point.&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Beastieball&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is still full of hidden information, though, most especially in the form of opponent actions. For example, while you might see your attack will do 100 damage when it lands, what you might not know is that your opponent is about to boost their defenses right before the attack connects, or put up a shield, negating the predicted damage. Players are allowed to see what all of their opponent’s options are, but they don’t know which one they’ll select, and this gap of knowledge leaves enough space for a universe of mind games that makes the game enriching and surprising.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A seredipitous result of this is how different single-player and multiplayer feel in &lt;em&gt;Beastieball.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; For an average player, the game’s depth of options usually means it’s a challenge to find the “best” choice, and that makes for fun encounters that feel almost puzzle-like from turn to turn.  But the opponent AI is quite logical, which means it’s usually quite predictable, effectively negating the existence of any hidden information. Opportunistic players can take advantage of that to claw a victory out even when they’re quite underpowered - I expect to see speedrunners crack the story mode wide open someday. Opponent players are a totally different beast, though - they can act intentionally unpredictably, creating surprising and chaotic matches where victory and defeat often come down to figuring out not what’s on the board, but what’s going on in your opponent’s head.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As with everything, there’s no “correct” way to design hidden information. It’s a problem with as many unique shapes as there are games. But I certainly had fun challenging myself to explore it further with this game. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Designing Turn-based Volleyball for Beastieball</title>
        <published>2023-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/designing-turn-based-volleyball-for/"/>
        <id>https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/designing-turn-based-volleyball-for/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/designing-turn-based-volleyball-for/">&lt;p&gt;Hello! I took a bit of a break from writing devlogs after funding our Kickstarter. We’ve been having fun diving back into Beastieball with newfound energy after finally revealing it and seeing all the love pour out :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve been holding a lot of thoughts about this game close to my chest for a long time. So many that it’s a bit daunting to actually sit down and try to unpack it all for a newsletter now! But, I think it’s time I talked a little bit about what inspired its unique turn-based volleyball system design. Many details really won’t make sense to dive into until the full game is available, and others still won’t all fit into one brief newsletter. This is a topic I’m passionate about and I expect I’ll return to it in future newsletters.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Why Turn-Based?&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve wanted to make a game about “building a team” for a LONG time; it’s a seed that I’d been cultiviating for nearly 10 years, slowly working out the practical details of how to build the game I was dreaming of.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the fundamental themes of “building a team” comes from learning about and deeply understanding each of the team members so that you can get the most out of their potential as individuals and in combination. Player’s success in my dream game had to be based on them forming this kind of understandning.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;em&gt;Screenshot from Nintendo Switch Sports&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;In any typical sports or action game, success is based on player reflexes, and you always overcome challenges by “getting good” and mastering the action, physics or controls better. Even in games that combine action elements with RPG elements, like Dark Souls, or active-turn-based RPGs like &lt;em&gt;Superstar Saga&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Super Mario RPG, &lt;&#x2F;em&gt;there’s a sort of friction; after losing to a difficult boss, you’re often caught between trying again with your current equipment and just playing a bit better, or backing off and grinding for a bit to get a statistical edge. These games are hugely popular and engaging, but I came to understand that in my game I wanted none of this friction. Success and failure had to come down to your understanding of your team, and how well you strategized around them. And so the game &lt;em&gt;had&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; to be turn-based!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I had figured out this much, but was stuck there in my thinking for a long time, because I couldn’t decide what turn-based thing I wanted the team to &lt;em&gt;do. &lt;&#x2F;em&gt;Obviously there are lots of turn-based war and battle games out there and it would have been easy enough to make another one of those, but I wanted to challenge myself to explore new directions, if only to make something more creatively stimulating for me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;2.png&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Haikyuu&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t figure it out until I saw the anime &lt;em&gt;Haikyuu&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; in 2020, which pretty much wrapped together all the themes of teamwork and personality chemistry that I’d been trying to synthesize in my head. And perhaps most importantly, it showed me that volleyball is an inherently turn-based sport, with each side equally trading control of the ball. Suddenly my idea for a team-building RPG was starting to make sense.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Mind Games&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;At this point I had an explosion of ideas and I was rapidly prototyping game designs. There were hundreds of decisions made about Beastieball around this time and I’d like to examine more of them in future articles, but for now I want to highlight one innovation that became a key feature for this game.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It started from thinking about what the essense of strategy is in the context of sports. Obviously there is the larger game plan; each player on a sports team has a specialty, ie. one player might be the designated point scorer and one might be there to play defense or disrupt the opponents. But in the micro, reflex, moment-to-moment decision making, it all comes down to mind games. If you can anticipate the very next thing your opponent will do, then you can move to block that choice and get an advantage; like making a block in volleyball, or intercepting a pass in basketball or soccer. High-level sports is not just about who is faster or stronger, but how effective you are at misdrecting your opponent and being able to move in a way they can’t anticipate or react to. I would say fighting games are best known for isolating and elevating this aspect of competitive games. I was interested in finding a way to make this part of the very DNA of Beastieball, giving players an opportunity to call out what their opponent will do, or misdirect them, to gain a statistical advantage.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;3.png&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;This was the basis for the lane-based targetting system. Rather than targetting an opponent, you hit the ball across a lane or row of the field, and the attack is received by the first Beastie standing in the ball’s path. Beastie’s field position has an impact on their power and defense, too; Beasties at the net do boosted damage but take extra damage, too. Altogether it adds just a tiny bit of complexity and ambiguity, enough to create space for mind games.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While you prepare you offense, the opponent always has the chance to take a defensive action which is revealed right before the attack lands. This creates opportunities for the opponent to swap out who is on the field, or reposition their board to change the outcome of the attack. Similarly, as the attacker, you’re trying to anticipate what the opponent might do to defend, and often it ends up being “better” to pick a “worse” attacking lane that your opponent is less likely to predict and defend against. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The sports-like format of the game is limiting in some ways, because the pace of the game is so tightly constrained; exactly ONE attack is made every turn, no more, no less. This is different from other strategy games where you might have some turns where you stall out and build resources, and other turns where you attack from multiple fronts simultaeously. I tried to lean into this weird property of the game and turn it into a strength, by making every attack interaction have a bit of build-up and surprise factor to it. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is probably enough from me for now. If you haven’t played the demo on Steam and are curious to learn more about the specifics of the sport systems, we made this helpful explainer video that shows a little bit more of it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;div id=&quot;youtube2-2ZRNHqqdx8w&quot; class=&quot;youtube-wrap&quot; data-attrs=&quot;{&amp;quot;videoId&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;2ZRNHqqdx8w&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;startTime&amp;quot;:null,&amp;quot;endTime&amp;quot;:null}&quot; data-component-name=&quot;Youtube2ToDOM&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;youtube-inner&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube-nocookie.com&#x2F;embed&#x2F;2ZRNHqqdx8w?rel=0&amp;amp;autoplay=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&amp;amp;enablejsapi=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; gesture=&quot;media&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; fullscreen&quot; allowautoplay=&quot;true&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; width=&quot;728&quot; height=&quot;409&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;iframe&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ll see you in the next newsletter! &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Game Musings - Quest Logs pt. 2</title>
        <published>2023-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-05-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/game-musings-quest-logs-pt-2/"/>
        <id>https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/game-musings-quest-logs-pt-2/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/game-musings-quest-logs-pt-2/">&lt;p&gt;This is a sequel to my &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;greglobanov.substack.com&#x2F;p&#x2F;game-musings-quest-logs&quot;&gt;previous post on quest logs&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; because… apparently I have more to say about them! I wanted to talk a little bit about how quest logs impact how a game is written, for better or worse.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The simple fact is, players always need to know what to do next. If they don’t have some guidance towards their current goal, the game quickly becomes frustrating. Quest logs fulfill this need automatically.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So in games that don’t have quest logs… you wind up writing a LOT of hints into the game text. This was absolutely true in Chicory; I’d estimate than about 1&#x2F;3rd or more of all the text in the game was gameplay instruction and quest hints. A quest-giving character can’t just tell you what they want; they have to remind you what they wanted every time you talk to them. And if you do a partial step, they have to recognize that and then give you the next partial hint. For every step of every quest, for every character. And then when you finish the quest, a clear resolution and “thank you for doing that!” so you know you’ve completed it. I put a lot of effort in to weave all this information naturally into each character’s story and unique voice, but beneath every conversation there’s always this rigid structure.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are definitely times where I bemoaned these limitations. Characters can never “just say something” - I had to think about what impression it will give the player, and whether they will mistake any passing comment as an actionable item. But, there’s also huge benefits to this in the long run, since players are actively engaged in all the text because it also contains all the info they need to beat the game. Even if flavor is only doled out between practical information, at least you know players are receiving it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Quest logs provide a tool for helping the player sort what’s relevant, so the writing has a lot more freedom. It doesn’t have nearly as much responsibility to relate to or connect with other elements of the game… so often it winds up becomes a lot more “book-like.” Indeed, it makes a lot more sense for games to be made this way when the teams are larger and writers aren’t working directly with the rest of the team; quest logs help paper over the little inconsistencies that can fall into the project from that kind of environment. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When done really well, the existence of “writing” and “quests” as two separate “systems” in the game actually can create really fun opportunities for new storytelling. For example, imagine an NPC who says “I heard Bob say something really rude about your friend,” and then you get a new side quest pop up: “Teach Bob a lesson.” That kind of little joke&#x2F;interaction gives you a satisfying bit of characterization. In a log-less game like Chicory, I’d have to heavy-handedly make the protagonist respond by saying “I better go teach that guy a lesson…” and instead of being a little joke it would just be kind of boring and straightforward.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There’s so much to get into! I find myself wanting to keep saying more about this but let’s leave it there. The important thing to remember is that no solution fits every project. Every decision you make as a creator always offers benefits as well as costs; the more aware you are of them, the better you can decide what solution best fits your goals.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Game Musings - Tears of the Kingdom</title>
        <published>2023-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-05-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/game-musings-tears-of-the-kingdom/"/>
        <id>https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/game-musings-tears-of-the-kingdom/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/game-musings-tears-of-the-kingdom/">&lt;p&gt;[I won’t spoil any story details or game mechanics here which aren’t apparent from the trailers.]&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a new format for the newsletter, but I thought it would be fun once in a while to talk about big game releases or interesting things I’ve been playing. I don’t often get to candidly share my thoughts on games… every game that releases is momentous and I generally like to focus on promoting things I think are cool. But, it’s also fun to talk candidly, and I can get a lot more nuanced here than on Twitter. (lol).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So anyway &lt;em&gt;Tears of the Kingdom&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is a &lt;em&gt;bizarre thing.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Firstly I’m struck by the technical achievement of it all. It boggles my mind that the game works so smoothly. Every individual part of its system is something that has been done somewhere before - building physics machines, rewinding simulations, crafting weapons… but I’ve never seen all of those things done all at once and in such a sprawling, open-world game where everything can interact. For example, it’s &lt;em&gt;crazy&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; that every single physics object can be rewound individually - but even cazier that they continue to interact with correct physics &lt;em&gt;while they’re rewinding&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and create new interactions. Gluing wheels and planks together, playing it all forward and backward, while having your player character climbing all over it at any angle, and it all works seamlessly and feels the way you expect it… I don’t think I can put into words how impressive it is. It terrifies me to think that they might not even have done anything that “smart,” per se, and instead just had to work crazy hard and methodically test SO MUCH to get it this stable. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The flip side is just how finnicky and janky the game is, overall - I can’t avoid mentioning this. It’s not a flaw, but an inevitable outcome of a game that works the way &lt;em&gt;Tears of the Kingdom&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; does. The player is given so much freedom and so much fine-tune control to do so many things at so many times that you can’t help but spend a lot of time experimenting and building ideas that don’t end up working. Nothing is as simple as bombing a cracked wall or hitting a switch… solving even the most basic puzzle takes some amount of thinking and labor to put together a solution. I adore that they took the game in this direction and trusted players with something so overwrought, but it’s undoubtedly a weird choice that will be a turn-off for many that enjoy what &lt;em&gt;Zelda&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; usually offers.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But, ultimately, I think a lot of what works in this game is only possible &lt;em&gt;because&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; it’s Zelda. If I imagine someone making a game like this from scratch in a new IP, I think players would have way less patience for it and would bounce off the steep learning curve and strange open-ended structure. But here, the familiar world of Zelda is a perfect canvas that this strange and beautiful thing is built on top of. I think that’s part of what gives you a hidden joy to fly over (and skip) a vast stretch of the world with your hand-crafted airplane, or to catapult a Korok across a canyon… these places and people are familiar, and that makes it extra fun to hold so many crowbars that can pry it open and pull it apart. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(I’d be really curious how this game feels to someone who’s never played a Zelda game before.)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It takes huge confidence and boldness to make something like this with an established and beloved world. I respect and admire every decision they made here. And I’m excited to keep playing it!!!!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(This is part of my “Game Musings” newsletter where I write thoughts about game design and development. If you just want news and updates on my projects, you can &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;greglobanov.substack.com&#x2F;account&quot;&gt;edit your subscription here.&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Game Musings - Quest logs</title>
        <published>2023-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/game-musings-quest-logs/"/>
        <id>https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/game-musings-quest-logs/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/game-musings-quest-logs/">&lt;p&gt;I think Quest Logs are really interesting. They’re something I tend to appreciate as a player, and I often see user reviews complaining when an open-ended game doesn’t have one. However… I also am trying to never put one into any game I ever make.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I talk about “quest logs” I’m talking about a game menu that maintains a clear record of all your current objectives and “quests” - the player’s active to-do list. Often this will keep a record of past finished quests too. On paper, this seems like a straightforwardly good idea. Having a quest log means players always know what they need to do, and they know where to go to find that information if they forget, like for example if they haven’t played the game in a couple weeks. Having info organized like this can be especially indispensible for larger games with many overlapping tasks.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The hidden downside of these logs are that they tokenize every interaction playrs can have with the story. For example, imagine meeting a character in a town who mentions offhandedly that their cat is missing and they’ve been feeling sad about it. Details like that can help enrich the world by giving you the feeling that other character have their own lives and problems going on alongside your own. But a player might naturally wonder whether that information was just for flavor, or whether it’s a problem that they are meant to solve - a quest to find the missing cat. A quest log system makes this completely unambiguous; if you suddenly get a popup saying “New Quest: Find the missing cat,” then you know now that it’s a problem to solve, and if the game has a quest log but doesn’t log this as a quest, then you know that it wasn’t meant to be a task for you.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If something is a task for the player, then they naturally will pay more attention to it. The unfortunate other side to this is, if something is “just flavor” and isn’t actually tied to any task or reward for the player then they’ll tend to ignore it. It’s very easy to get into a mode where you’re simply clicking through all the dialogue and interactions you can have with townspeople to see what actually lands in your Quest log as a to-do item, and then focusing on that in order to progress through the game. (I’ve done this in pretty much every game with a quest log). &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Amgiuity is “worse” for the player in the sense that they don’t always clearly know what they’re supposed to be doing, but “better” in that it actually forces them to pay more attention to the story of the game, and make their own inferences about what’s important. If there’s a missing cat the player can find, but they aren’t explicitly told that, then they get to have the thrill of finding that out organically, and the satisfaction of remembering that townsperson who said her cat was missing. But of course, it could be bad if it wasn’t really intended to be a quest, but a player wrongfully assumes that it is, and gets frustrated looking for a cat they’ll never find. Or perhaps worse, they *have* to find a missing cat to beat the game, but they missed the hidden cue about it when they talked to that one townsperson and now they’ll never figure out what they need to do without looking it up…&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All games have a hierarchy of what’s important and what isn’t, whether that hierarchy is exposed to the player or not. Athough I love the convenience of always knowing what my tasks are, I value games that allow space for ambiguity. Ultimately it makes for a more believable world, full of potential surprises and depths that you can uncover only through your own judgement and curiosity.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot more I could say about this, including how we approached this problem in Chicory (a sprawling, sidequest-filled, open-ended game with no formal quest log…) but I think I’ve already rambled enough in this one.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(This is part of my “Game Musings” newsletter where I write thoughts about game design and development. If you just want news and updates on my projects, you can &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;greglobanov.substack.com&#x2F;account&quot;&gt;edit your subscription here.&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Game Musings - Setting goals in open worlds</title>
        <published>2023-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/setting-goals-in-open-worlds/"/>
        <id>https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/setting-goals-in-open-worlds/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/setting-goals-in-open-worlds/">&lt;p&gt;Open-world type games are all the rage lately. I’ve recently played a lot of long-anticipated such titles like &lt;em&gt;Tchia&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; or the most recent &lt;em&gt;Pokemon&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; games, and I’m also eagerly awaiting the new &lt;em&gt;Zelda&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; game too. But &lt;em&gt;making&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; an open-world game is a process full of pitfalls! I wanted to share just one bit of wisdom I’ve gained from experience.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When making open-ended exploration titles, my intuition was simply to build lots of space filled with things to do, and present it all to player equally and let them decide how to approach it. The thinking was to inundate the player with options, so that they’d feel empowered and free.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But this actually had the opposite effect and made players feel totally lost, and ultimately, bored. Because if everything is equally important, then nothing is actually important. And without clear guidance on what they should be doing next, players quickly lose interest. Even when the answer was “you can do lots of things - just poke around and you’ll find fun stuff,” it’s just not a satisfying answer.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What I found works very well is to set very, very clear goals for the player with very, very clear steps toward progress. Make sure the player ALWAYS knows what the next step is, and&#x2F;or has easy access to find out.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It turns out that in open-world experiences, it’s not actually fun for things to be completely open. What &lt;em&gt;is&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; fun is to know what you’re supposed to do, and then having the choice of doing it or doing something else instead. Players who want to explore and “break the system” know what to avoid, and get the satisfiying feeling of playing outside the intended bounds of the game (even when they actually aren’t). And when players want an easy, direct checklist of things to do to move towards progress, the game offers that as well. I’ve found that when games offer both of these “modes” of experience, they are way more satisfying for way more people—because, it turns out, just about everybody feels both of these needs at different times, and when they have the freedom to switch how they’re approaching the game they’ll tend to stick with it longer and not get exhausted as easily.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot more I can say about this topic, but I will leave it here for now. Open-world style games are really, really fun to play and really, really hard to make—I’m excited to share more thoughts on them in the future.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(This is part of my “Game Musings” newsletter where I write thoughts about game design and development. If you just want news and updates on my projects, you can &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;greglobanov.substack.com&#x2F;account&quot;&gt;edit your subscription here.&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Game Musings - In-game editors</title>
        <published>2023-04-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-04-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/game-musings-in-game-editors/"/>
        <id>https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/game-musings-in-game-editors/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/game-musings-in-game-editors/">&lt;p&gt;Every project I’ve worked on for the last 8 or so years has started with creating an in-game editor. Even though I use Game Maker Studio 2, which ostensibly offers a nice visual interface and its own built-in “Room” editor (kind of a level editor), I strongly prefer to build my own. And I always start over and build it from scratch for each project.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I find the process extremely useful because the process of figuring out what the game is always goes hand in hand with figuring out how I want to make it. I care a lot about keeping my work process fun and creative - and ultimately, no universal game editor or level editor will ever be as powerful for building your specific project as one which you make yourself. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;For example, this was the Chicory level editor. Although the levels were pretty simple in that game, it still added a lot of character to the game that they were created in this custom, toy-like editor. I used the same system for “painting” levels that players used to “paint” in the game, so there’s a certain harmony of shapes in what players can create and how the world is shaped. Practically speaking, this also kept everything aligned to the same grid so that player drawings are always naturally aligned with the level geometry. It took a fair bit of time to set this up at first, but in the long term it made it so fast and easy to create more content for the game that it definitely sped things up overall.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another hidden benefit is that working this way skips the process of building your game. (Ie. the time it takes for the game to actually start after you hit “play” from the game editor you’re using). Being able to flip back and forth between editing and playing the game instantaneously without restarting is a HUGE advantage for time and just general mentality&#x2F;flow. When playtesting the game with a friend in-person, if they ran into an issue, I could just lean over, open up the editor right in front of them, fix the issue, then put them back in the game - all within seconds. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The joy I get from building editors definitely grew a lot after I first played &lt;em&gt;Super Mario Maker&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;, which replicates this experience for building 2D Mario levels. It opened my eyes to how fun it could be to make games, and I’ve held that in my mind ever since. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(This is part of my “Game Musings” newsletter where I write thoughts about game design and development. If you just want news and updates on my projects, you can &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;greglobanov.substack.com&#x2F;account&quot;&gt;edit your subscription here.&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Game Musings - Finding your game&#x27;s core</title>
        <published>2023-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/finding-your-games-core/"/>
        <id>https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/finding-your-games-core/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/finding-your-games-core/">&lt;p&gt;This is a re-framing of advice that I once got from my beloved friend Maddy Thorson, but it also rapidly advanced how I approached my projects, so I wanted to share it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The advice is essentially just that, when planning out your game, you should learn what the core idea of your game is - the central pillar that defines what your goal with the project is. Knowing that makes iteration and prototyping easier because any time you’re trying out a new idea for your project, you can ask whether or not it contributes to the core idea of your game. If it doesn’t support the core idea, then you can easily discard it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For example, in &lt;em&gt;Chicory: A Colorful Tale,&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; I wanted to make a game where players could be creative and draw freely as their main method of interacting with the world. I tried a lot of ideas early on that broke this rule. At one point I thought the game might be about the world missing bridges or other landmarks which the player had to fill in. But this made the game into a simple lock-and-key “fill in the blanks” experience where your actual drawings were meaningless, and instead were a means to a more important end (replace the missing landmarks). This led me to the idea that the world has lost its color, so that your drawings themselves were the “solution” to the problem in the game, and not a means of fixing some other problem. There were a lot of possible “drawing games” that Chicory could have become which would have been perfectly OK, but by focusing on the experience I wanted players to have, I narrowed in on exactly what pieces the game needed to have and which it didn’t.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lately, I feel like I’ve met more and more designers working on projects that don’t have a clear core. Sometimes this is because the game is very complex, like an elaborate simulation game whose “fun” only becomes clear through many overlapping systems all working in harmony. Other times it’s because the game is coming from a larger team with a lot of different cool ideas mashed together, or it’s based on a really cool story&#x2F;visual aesthetic that shows really well on social media but doesn’t easily lend itself to generating player experiences. As powerful hardware and game making tools have gotten more accessible, games have gotten bigger over the years, and I think that’s had a negative effect on creators’ ability to hone in on what the goal of their project is. It’s easy for a project to spend years going in circles as it picks up ideas like a Katamari ball, only to drop most of those ideas once it finds its core and starts going towards an end point. (Or, worse, never finishes. Or carries all those ideas to the finish line, resulting in a bloated end product).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For games that are based on a really broad idea or feeling, it can be really hard to hone in on what you’re making, and that can have disastrous effects if you let the problem fester. In the past, I’ve found it useful to hone in on one specific cool idea or interaction that inspired me to want to make the game in the first place - and then decontruct &lt;em&gt;why&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; that idea is cool to me, which aspects of it are interchangable, and which are not. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;One way or another, if you ever want people to play your game, you need to finish it; to finish it, you need to have a plan to get there; and to form a plan, you need to know where you’re going.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Game Musings - Squishy and crunchy</title>
        <published>2023-04-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-04-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/game-musings-squishy-and-crunchy/"/>
        <id>https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/game-musings-squishy-and-crunchy/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/game-musings-squishy-and-crunchy/">&lt;p&gt;“Squishy” and “crunchy” are two words I use a lot and hear used a lot when discussing games with other designers. It’s a useful way of understanding the structure of games, so I wanted to talk about what they mean to me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Crunchiness” emerges when games use smaller or fewer numbers, have fewer pieces in general, and have a more limited set of interactions. “Squishiness” describes the opposite, when games have broader possibilities, with lots of fluidity and amorphousness. For example, you could think about a complex strategy game like X-COM or Starcraft, with lots of moving creatures and structures and stats and numbers to keep track of (squishy), as opposed to Chess, which all takes place on a tiny 8x8 grid and every piece dies in just one hit (crunchy). &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Early in my career, I internalized that “crunchy” games were strictly better, and that the way to improve a game design was to cut down on elements and make the numbers smaller until I found the purest, simplest expression of that game idea. With experience I’ve come to feel that neither is better, but both offer useful pathways to refine a game. Crunchy games tend to be more concise and satisfying, whereas squishiness lends itself to experiences that are open-ended and surprising. I’m also starting to feel that in general, squishier games actually have more mass appeal than crunchy games. That’s one way to characterize why expansive, squishy, open-world titles like &lt;em&gt;Elden Ring&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Breath of the Wild&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; wound up being such standout successes for long-running franchises that had previously been much crunchier. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The flipside to this is that squishier games are much, much harder to make. This works against some intuition; you’d expect it to be easier to work in game genres that organically create tons of squishy permutations and interactions (roguelikes, card games, fighting games, open world games…) because there’s so many cool things that can happen, that even if there isn’t designed intention behind every interaction, players are sure to find something fun in there. But when a game is full of ideas that aren’t thought through, it tends to produce a lot of mediocrity, which colors players’ perception of the experience, even if there are really cool ideas in there too. Lots of “noise” in a game can drown out the underlying structure and make it harder for players to keep track of what they’re supposed to pay attention to or what the point is. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think squishy games tend to succeed when designers put an &lt;em&gt;enormously greater&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; amount of intention and thought into them, so that what parses as “squishiness” in the final game is actually a superstructure of tiny, crunchy design decisions. I think this has some parallels with my previous post on how I always aim to have the smallest wordcount I can. Even when something is jam-packed full of ideas, it’s most worthwhile when all those ideas are fully thought through.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is a fine balance here, because to make something that feels squishy you actually &lt;em&gt;need&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; there to be undesigned space where things can interact unpredictably. Crafting larger games like this always falls into a difficult conversation of “what do I actually design, and what do I leave open?” Ultimately there’s no true right answer, which is what makes it such a difficult problem. Often you can only arrive at your game’s answer through a slow process of addition, subtraction and testing. But when something in my game feels too linear, simple or predictable then I know it probably needs more squishiness… and when it’s all feeling samey, murky, or amorphous then I start looking for ways to crunch it down.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Game Musings - Watch your wordcount!</title>
        <published>2023-04-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-04-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/game-musings-watch-your-wordcount/"/>
        <id>https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/game-musings-watch-your-wordcount/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/game-musings-watch-your-wordcount/">&lt;p&gt;I get asked my advice on game writing fairly often, and I feel this is the most specific, useful advice I can impart.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;CUT OUT AS MANY WORDS AS POSSIBLE FROM YOUR GAME!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Given that my projects tend to be sprawling, over-written adventure games I think this advice comes as a surprise to people who ask me for it. But I promise that all my games could have been a lot wordier, and a lot worse for it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Whenever I write a conversation or scene for a game, I probably spend the most time going over it and finding every little thing I can remove while retaining the original intention or message. For example, normal conversations will be full of small polite-isms and connecting phrases like “Thanks,” “Oh, also…” and that sort of thing. Removing those might feel unnatural at first, but once they’re gone you’ll be surprised that you don’t notice them missing. I don’t just remove useless turns of phrase - any time I can find a way to communicate even a very complicated idea in fewer words, I will do it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a good rule of thumb for writing in general, because it helps you express your point more clearly. But I think it’s especially critical for (non-VN) games, where people have the expectation of interaction. Every line of text you add increases the time players spend waiting and adds another moment where they have to press A to advance. Players can get exhausted of story very quickly… and if your game is giving them words that don’t feel necessary, they’ll start ignoring them. Once a player starts clicking through conversations without reading them, you’ve basically lost their trust, and all the work you put into your game’s text becomes worthless.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I examine every word in my games from this perspective, questioning if it needs to be there and what it contributes. And if I’m trying to get across a big idea in a scene that I can’t communicate succinctly, I’ll find a way to split it into multiple scenes and spread it out over a longer stretch of the game. My goal is always to leave players with the impression that every bit of text in my games matters, and that they should be paying attention to it. Otherwise, why bother having it?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
