<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
      <title>Wishes Ultd. - chicory</title>
      <link>https://gl326.github.io/web/</link>
      <description>Indie games by Greg Lobanov &amp; friends</description>
      <generator>Zola</generator>
      <language>en</language>
      <atom:link href="https://gl326.github.io/web/tags/chicory/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
          <title>Chicory 4-year anniversary + Tote Bag!</title>
          <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/chicory-4-year-anniversary-tote-bag/</link>
          <guid>https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/chicory-4-year-anniversary-tote-bag/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/chicory-4-year-anniversary-tote-bag/">&lt;p&gt;It’s been almost 4 years since Chicory first launched on Steam and Playstation… At the time I recall there was a powerful anticipation for the game within our niche little community. But we couldn’t have foreseen just how large its impact was going to be and the kind of response it was going to get from players during a difficult pandemic year in 2021. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s still pretty mind-blowing to look back at the accolades it received. &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.destructoid.com&#x2F;destructoids-award-for-best-overall-game-of-2021-goes-to&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Destructoid&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.giantbomb.com&#x2F;giant-bomb-game-of-the-year-2021&#x2F;3015-12822&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Giant Bomb&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; both named Chicory as their #1 Game of the Year in 2021. Looking at other games that have received the same selection, you see stuff like &lt;em&gt;Zelda, The Last of Us, Elden Ring, Grand Theft Auto&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;… far as I can tell Chicory is the only GOTY on either list that wasn’t a million+ dollar budget mainstream success. Somehow our weird little indie game made by a few friends off a modest Kickstarter campaign was able to reach many people and stand out as a game worth remembering. There were like a hundred other accolades worth celebrating at the time (getting shortlisted for the Indie Games Festival grand prize was a pretty special bucket list item to check off) but those GOTY noms have particularly stuck with me because of how weird they are.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ANYWAYS, in celebration of our strange and beautiful little painting dog game turning 4, we’ve got a new tote bag to share with you!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;button-wrapper&quot; data-attrs=&quot;{&amp;quot;url&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;theyetee.com&#x2F;collections&#x2F;chicory&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;text&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;Shop Chicory merch here!&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;action&amp;quot;:null,&amp;quot;class&amp;quot;:null}&quot; data-component-name=&quot;ButtonCreateButton&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;button primary&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;theyetee.com&#x2F;collections&#x2F;chicory&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Shop Chicory merch here!&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You may recognize the design as the album art for the game soundtrack. The original art was hand-painted by Alexis, the game’s character artist and animator (who then went on to direct all the creature design and animation in our follow-up, &lt;em&gt;Beastieball&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;). For the tote bag we processed her vivid and complex art town to just 4 colors, which was not trivial to do, but after seeing the results printed in person I was pretty blown away. I’m not really a guy who gets excited about tote bags but this one looks REALLY good. The print is very vivid and the limited palette evokes the look of the actual game in a funnily authentic way.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thanks to everybody for supporting our weird little team making our weird little games. It’s a very rare and fortunate thing to get to make our dream projects and pursue our craft to make the best things we can imagine without compromise for market viability or demographic appeal or whatever. This game is really special to us, and even if we tried I don’t think we could ever make something quite like it again.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thanks forever,&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Greg &amp;amp; The Chicory Team&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Chicory PHYSICAL EDITIONS available now for Switch and PS5!</title>
          <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/chicory-physical-editions-available/</link>
          <guid>https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/chicory-physical-editions-available/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/chicory-physical-editions-available/">&lt;p&gt;YES!!!! Pre-orders are now available for Chicory physical game editions for Nintendo Switch and Sony Playstation 5. &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Collector’s Edition comes with a ton of extra one-of-a-kind goodies. :) The Coloring Book in particular has a ton of new pieces commissioned from fans and friends, featuring some of our favorite characters in new scenes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’ve been working pretty hard on these in the background and are thrilled to finally show this off to you. It’s a special thing for us as a team, because we all adore this game and selfishly want to have physical copies of our own, heh heh… &lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These will only be available for a limited time, until December 15!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;button-wrapper&quot; data-attrs=&quot;{&amp;quot;url&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;limitedrungames.com&#x2F;products&#x2F;chicory-a-colorful-tale-standard-edition-switch-ps5&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;text&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;Pre-order your physical copy here!&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;action&amp;quot;:null,&amp;quot;class&amp;quot;:null}&quot; data-component-name=&quot;ButtonCreateButton&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;button primary&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;limitedrungames.com&#x2F;products&#x2F;chicory-a-colorful-tale-standard-edition-switch-ps5&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Pre-order your physical copy here!&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Chicory is now available on Game Pass!</title>
          <pubDate>Tue, 30 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/chicory-is-now-available-on-game/</link>
          <guid>https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/chicory-is-now-available-on-game/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/chicory-is-now-available-on-game/">&lt;p&gt;What’s up gamers! If you’re a Microsoft Game Pass subscriber you can now access &lt;em&gt;Chicory: A Colorful Tale &lt;&#x2F;em&gt;on XBox consoles or on Windows!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This release also comes with a lot of new fixes and localizations to Japanese, Chinese and Korean (!!!!)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have been working on this new version of the game for a long time and are still working on getting it out on every other platform. It will be available everywhere &lt;em&gt;as soon as possible. &lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Be seeing you in the Picnic Province!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;-Chicory team&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Introducing... the Official Chicory Artbook!</title>
          <pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/introducing-the-official-chicory/</link>
          <guid>https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/introducing-the-official-chicory/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/introducing-the-official-chicory/">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;button-wrapper&quot; data-attrs=&quot;{&amp;quot;url&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;banov.itch.io&#x2F;chicory-a-colorful-art-book&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;text&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;Check it out HERE!&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;action&amp;quot;:null,&amp;quot;class&amp;quot;:null}&quot; data-component-name=&quot;ButtonCreateButton&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;button primary&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;banov.itch.io&#x2F;chicory-a-colorful-art-book&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Check it out HERE!&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s been a long time coming. We’re proud to reveal this 189-page official digital artbook for Chicory :) We had promised to (and wanted to!) make this for Kickstarter backers… but what started off as a seemingly simple project became a long journey for us. We collected art and notes from many years of development and worked with a fabulous layout artist (Hayley Ng!) to make a professional final package.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are concept drawings, sketches, articles, interviews, never-before-seen characters and all manner of juicy process details to uncover in here. We wanted to give fans a new peek into the world, but we also wanted to share our process in a way that we think any creator can get inspired by.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We’re very proud of this and are excited to finally share it with you all!!! We hope you love it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>We finally made a Chicory plush</title>
          <pubDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/we-finally-made-a-chicory-plush/</link>
          <guid>https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/we-finally-made-a-chicory-plush/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://gl326.github.io/web/blog/we-finally-made-a-chicory-plush/">&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;button-wrapper&quot; data-attrs=&quot;{&amp;quot;url&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.fangamer.com&#x2F;products&#x2F;chicory-pizza-plush&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;text&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;Check it out!&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;action&amp;quot;:null,&amp;quot;class&amp;quot;:null}&quot; data-component-name=&quot;ButtonCreateButton&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;button primary&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.fangamer.com&#x2F;products&#x2F;chicory-pizza-plush&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Check it out!&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This has been a long time coming!!! Getting Pizza’s weird, beany head and body shape just right took some real time and effort. Fangamer also went above and beyond with cool features, like magnets in the hand + brush to make them all stick to each other, and, yes… the entire plush is made of washable, markerable material so you can go nuts and draw all over them. It’s kind of cute, and kind of deranged, and we love it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thank you Fangamer for this incredible opportunity. I genuinely don’t know how many of these they’ll make or how long they’ll be available so don’t hesitate to check it out.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(I migrated all my newsletters to this new consolidated one. If you only want updates on certain topics you can &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;greglobanov.substack.com&#x2F;account&quot;&gt;edit your subscription here.&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;</description>
      </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
